<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_red.png" type="Source">
    <name>TrimGalore</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        A wrapper tool around <a href="https://cutadapt.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">Cutadapt</a> and <a href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">FastQC</a> to consistently apply quality and adapter trimming to FastQ files, with some extra functionality for MspI-digested RRBS-type (Reduced Representation Bisufite-Seq) libraries.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
		Trim Galore! is a wrapper script to automate quality and adapter trimming as well as quality control, with some added functionality to remove biased methylation positions for RRBS sequence files (for directional, non-directional (or paired-end) sequencing). It's main features are:
		<br></br>
		Trim Galore is now also available from <a href="https://github.com/FelixKrueger/TrimGalore">GitHub</a>. You are invited to leave comments, feature request or bug reports over there! 
		<br></br>
		<br></br>
		
		
    	&#8226;For adapter trimming, Trim Galore! uses the first 13 bp of Illumina standard adapters ('AGATCGGAAGAGC') by default (suitable for both ends of paired-end libraries), but accepts other adapter sequence, too
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;For MspI-digested RRBS libraries, Trim Galore! performs quality and adapter trimming in two subsequent steps. This allows it to remove 2 additional bases that contain a cytosine which was artificially introduced in the end-repair step during the library preparation
   		
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;For any kind of FastQ file other than MspI-digested RRBS, Trim Galore! can perform single-pass adapter- and quality trimming
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;The Phred quality of basecalls and the stringency for adapter removal can be specified individually
    	    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Trim Galore! can remove sequences if they become too short during the trimming process. For paired-end files Trim Galore! removes entire sequence pairs if one (or both) of the two reads became shorter than the set length cutoff. Reads of a read-pair that are longer than a given threshold but for which the partner read has become too short can optionally be written out to single-end files. This ensures that the information of a read pair is not lost entirely if only one read is of good quality
    	    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Trim Galore! can trim paired-end files by 1 additional bp from the 3' end of all reads to avoid problems with invalid alignments with Bowtie 1
    	    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Trim Galore! accepts and produces standard or gzip compressed FastQ files
    	   	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;FastQC can be run on the resulting output files once trimming has completed (optional)
    	    	
    	<br></br>
    	<br></br>

		Source: <a href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</a>
		</intro>
        
        
        <option name="Gzip output">Compress the output file with GZIP. If the input files are GZIP-compressed
                        the output files will automatically be GZIP compressed as well. As of v0.2.8 the
                        compression will take place on the fly.
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Adapter sequence">Adapter sequence to be trimmed. If not specified explicitly, Trim Galore will
                        try to auto-detect whether the Illumina universal, Nextera transposase or Illumina
                        small RNA adapter sequence was used. Also see '--illumina', '--nextera' and
                        '--small_rna'. If no adapter can be detected within the first 1 million sequences
                        of the first file specified Trim Galore defaults to '--illumina'.
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Adapter sequence for read file 2">Optional adapter sequence to be trimmed off read 2 of paired-end files. This
                        option requires '--paired' to be specified as well. If the libraries to be trimmed
                        are smallRNA then a2 will be set to the Illumina small RNA 5' adapter automatically
                        (GATCGTCGGACT).
                        </option>
                       
        <option name="Preset adapter">Choose from one of 4 preset adapters:<br></br>AUTOMATIC:  Trim Galore will
                        try to auto-detect whether the Illumina universal, Nextera transposase or Illumina
                        small RNA adapter sequence was used. If no adapter can be detected within the first 1 million sequences
                        of the first file specified Trim Galore defaults to '--illumina'.
                        <br></br><br></br>illumina: Adapter sequence to be trimmed is the first 13bp of the Illumina universal adapter
                        'AGATCGGAAGAGC' instead of the default auto-detection of adapter sequence.
                        <br></br><br></br>nextera: Adapter sequence to be trimmed is the first 12bp of the Nextera adapter
                        'CTGTCTCTTATA' instead of the default auto-detection of adapter sequence.
                        <br></br><br></br>small_rna: Adapter sequence to be trimmed is the first 12bp of the Illumina Small RNA 3' Adapter
                        'TGGAATTCTCGG' instead of the default auto-detection of adapter sequence. Selecting
                        to trim smallRNA adapters will also lower the --length value to 18bp. If the smallRNA
                        libraries are paired-end then a2 will be set to the Illumina small RNA 5' adapter
                        automatically (GATCGTCGGACT) unless -a 2 had been defined explicitly. 
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Quality">Trim low-quality ends from reads in addition to adapter removal. For
                        RRBS samples, quality trimming will be performed first, and adapter
                        trimming is carried in a second round. Other files are quality and adapter
                        trimmed in a single pass. The algorithm is the same as the one used by BWA
                        (Subtract INT from all qualities; compute partial sums from all indices
                        to the end of the sequence; cut sequence at the index at which the sum is
                        minimal). Default Phred score: 20.
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Stringency">Overlap with adapter sequence required to trim a sequence. Defaults to a
                        very stringent setting of 1, i.e. even a single bp of overlapping sequence
                        will be trimmed off from the 3' end of any read.
                        </option>   
                        
        <option name="Error rate">Maximum allowed error rate (no. of errors divided by the length of the matching
                        region) (default: 0.1)
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Length">Discard reads that became shorter than length INT because of either
                        quality or adapter trimming. A value of '0' effectively disables
                        this behaviour. Default: 20 bp.
						<br></br><br></br>
                        For paired-end files, both reads of a read-pair need to be longer than
                        &lt;INT&gt; bp to be printed out to validated paired-end files (see option --paired).
                        If only one read became too short there is the possibility of keeping such
                        unpaired single-end reads (see --retain_unpaired). Default pair-cutoff: 20 bp.
                        </option>        
                        
         <option name="Additional TrimGalore options">Additional TrimGalore options not contained above. 
         				Please consult the official TrimGalore documentation for assistance in setting these options.
         </option>                                                                  
       
        <tab name="FastQC Options">
            <option name="Folder for output files">Create all output files in the specified output directory.
                    Please note that this directory must exist as the program
                    will not create it.  If this option is not set then the 
                    output file for each sequence file is created in the same
                    directory as the sequence file which was processed.
		</option>	
		
        <option name="Number of threads">Specifies the number of files which can be processed
                    simultaneously.  Each thread will be allocated 250MB of
                    memory so you shouldn't run more threads than your
                    available memory will cope with, and not more than
                    6 threads on a 32 bit machine
        </option>
        
        <option name="Additional FastQC options.">For all additional FastQC options not offered above. 
        			Please consult the official FastQC documentation for assistance in configuring these options."
        </option>
        </tab>
        
        <tab name="Preference page">
        	<option name="HTE">
        		Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        		Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        	</option>
        </tab>
   
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port name">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1 <br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path to ReadFile2.</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to TrimmedReadFile1<br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path to TrimmedReadFile2.</outPort>
    </ports>   
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
