<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source">
    <name>SnpSift</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        This node is a wrapper for the SnpSift toolbox.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
			This node is a wrapper for the <a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html">SnpSift</a> toolbox.
			Various tools allow you to filter and manipulate VCF files (annotated by snpEff).
		</intro>
        
        <tab name="Options">
        	<option name="Select tool">
        		<ul>
        			<li>
        				<a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html#filter">Filter</a>:
        				SnpSift filter is one of the most useful SnpSift commands. 
        				Using SnpSift filter you can filter VCF files using arbitrary expressions.
        			</li>
        			<li>
        				<a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html#annotate">Annotate</a>:
        				Annotate using fields from another VCF file (e.g. dbSnp, 1000 Genomes projects, ClinVar, ExAC, etc.). 
        			</li>
        			<li>
        				<a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html#TsTv">TsTv</a>:
        				Calculate the transition to transversion ratios for each sample.
        			</li>
        			<li>
        				<a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html#Intervals">Intervals</a>:
        				This tool is used to extract variants that intersect any interval. 
        			</li>
        			<li>
        				<a href="http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/SnpSift.html#dbNSFP">dbNSFP</a>:
        				The dbNSFP is an integrated database of functional predictions from multiple algorithms (SIFT, Polyphen2, LRT and MutationTaster, PhyloP and GERP++, etc.). 
        			</li>
        			<li>
        				Other: Use another tool by specifying an individual command.
        			</li>
        		</ul>
        	</option>
        	<option name="Individual Command">
        		You can specify an individual command and parameters that are provided by SnpSift, e.g. hwe -q.
        		The output of the specified tool is written into the selected file.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Filter">
        	<option name="Filter criteria">
        		Set your filter criteria according to the syntax of SnpSift.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Annotate">
        	<option name="VCF file providing annotations">
        		Set a path to a VCF file that provides annotations to be assigned to variants in the input VCF file.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Do not annotate INFO fields">
        		INFO fields are not annotated, i.e. only the ID field is annotated.
        	</option>
        	<option name="List of INFO fields">
        		Annotate using a list of info fields (list is a comma separated list of fields). Default: ALL.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Further annotate flags">
        		Here, you can specify further flags that are supported by the annotate tool.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Intervals">
        	<option name="Specify interval file">
        		Select a BED file that defines intervals.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Exclude entries in intervals">
        		If this option is checked, all variants that intersect one of the given intervals will be excluded from the output.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="dbNFSP">
        	<option name="Specify dbNFSP database">
        		Set the path to the gzipped and indexed dbNFSP.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Include empty values">
        		Annotate fields, even if the database has an empty value (annotates using '.' for empty).
        	</option>
        	<option name="List of field names">
        		A comma separated list of fields to add.
        		Type "java -jar SnpSift.jar dbnfsp" within your terminal to see the full list of default fields.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Further dbnsfp flags">
        		Here, you can specify further flags that are supported by the dbnsfp tool.
        	</option>
        </tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input VCF file">
        	Cell 0: Input VCF file. Some SnpSift tools require files annotated by snpEff.
        </inPort>

        <outPort index="0" name="Output file">
        	Cell 0: The format of the output file depends on the chosen tool.
        </outPort>

    </ports>    
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">
        	The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool.
        </view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
