<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>VEPFilter</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        This node filters VCF files annotated by VEP.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	The VEPFilter enables the filtering of VCF files annotated by VEP.
        	The output is a VCF file containing the variants that have passed the filters.
        </intro>
        
        <tab name="Options">
        	<option name="Filter by Consequence">
        		Here, you can select Sequence Ontology (SO) terms to filter variants according to their predicted consequences.
        		The shown SO terms are ranked by their impact, from HIGH to MODIFIER.
        		The <a href="http://www.ensembl.org/info/genome/variation/predicted_data.html#consequences">VEP documentation</a> gives detailed descriptions for each SO term.
        		Press the Ctrl or Shift key to select multiple consequences.
        		If you don't want to filter by consequences, select 'NONE'.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Choose LOF terms">
        		This button allows you to easily select all SO terms that define loss-of-function (LOF) variants.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Further filtering conditions">
        		Further filters can be specified.
        		For more information, see <a href="http://www.ensembl.org/info/docs/tools/vep/script/vep_filter.html">http://www.ensembl.org/info/docs/tools/vep/script/vep_filter.html</a>
        	</option>
        	<option name="Folder for output files">
        		Set the path to the folder where the filtered VCF file will be stored.<br />
            	If "Overwrite" is checked, existing files will be overwritten.
        	</option>
        </tab>		
        <tab name="Preference page">
        	<option name="HTE">
        		Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        		Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to filter_vep.pl">
        		Set the path to the script used to filter VEP annotations.
        		It can be found in the VEP installation in the ensembl-tools-release../scripts/variant_effect_predictor folder.
       	 	</option>
       	 </tab>	
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input VCF">
        	Cell 0: Path to VCF file.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Filtered VCF">
        	Cell 0: Path to filtered VCF file.
        </outPort>
    </ports>
    
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">
        	The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool.
        </view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
