<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>GATKVariantFiltration</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Filter variant calls based on INFO and FORMAT annotations.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This node is based on the VariantFiltration tool of GATK which enables hard-filtering variant calls based on certain criteria.
        	Records are hard-filtered by changing the value in the FILTER field to something other than PASS.
        	Use the GATK ExcludeVariants node to remove the filtered variants.<br />
        	For further information, see the GATK documentation of the <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/guide/tooldocs/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_filters_VariantFiltration.php">VariantFiltration</a> walker.
        </intro>
        
 		 <tab name="VariantFiltration">
        	<option name="Filter INFO fields">
        		Filter variants according to values of the INFO fields. 
				Variants that match any one of the given conditions will be tagged with 'Filter Name' in the FILTER field.
				Further conditions can be defined in the 'Additional Filter Options' field.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Filter FORMAT fields">
        		Filter genotypes according to values of the FORMAT fields. 
				Genotypes that match any one of the given conditions will be tagged with 'Filter Name' in the FT field of the FORMAT fields.
				Further conditions can be defined in the 'Additional Filter Options' field.
				If the box is checked, filtered genotypes are set to no-call.
				Note that allele counts are not recomputed after filtering.
        	</option>
        	For further information on how to apply hard filters, see <a href="http://gatkforums.broadinstitute.org/gatk/discussion/2806/howto-apply-hard-filters-to-a-call-set"> http://gatkforums.broadinstitute.org/gatk/discussion/2806/howto-apply-hard-filters-to-a-call-set</a>
		</tab>
		<tab name= "GATK">
        <option name="GATK Memory">
        Set the maximum Java heap size (in GB).
        </option>
        <option name="Path to BED file">
        Tick this option in order to call variants in certain genomic regions. 
        You have to specify the intervals in a text file in BED format
        (Format explained at <a href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/FAQ/FAQformat.html"> http://genome.ucsc.edu/FAQ/FAQformat.html</a>)
        and select the file in the file browser.
        </option>
        <option name="Further options">
        Set additional command line flags for the GATKVariantFiltration.
        </option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Preference page">
        <option name="HTE">
        	Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        	Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        </option>
        <option name="Path to reference sequence">
        	Set the path to the reference reference sequence.
        	This will be done automatically if the path is already defined in the preference page.  
        </option>	
        <option name="Path to GATK jar file">
        	Set the path to GenomeAnalysisTK.jar.
        	This will be done automatically if the path is already defined in the preference page.  
       	</option>
       	</tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input VCF">
        	Input VCF file
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Filtered VCF">
        	Cell 0: VCF file with adjusted FILTER fields
        	Note that filtered variants can be removed using the GATK ExcludeVariants node.
        </outPort>
    </ports>
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
    </views>   
</knimeNode>
