<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_red.png" type="Source">
<name>RawReadManipulator</name>
   
<shortDescription>
	The RawReadManipulator filters reads from fastQ/fastA files.
</shortDescription>
    
<fullDescription>
	<intro>
		This node is based on the RawReadManipulator toll (written by Jonathan Hoser).
		It filter reads from a fastQ or fastA file and creates a new fastQ/fastA file in the same directory, unless otherwise specified.
	</intro>
	
    <tab name="Options">
        <option name="HTE"> Set a threshold for repeated execution.Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        </option>
        <option name="Filter settings file">
        Choose whether to use filter settings calculated by FASTQC (in-port) or to specify your own filter settings file.
        If you decide to use your own filter settings, you have to set the path to the filter settings file.
        </option>
        <option name="Barcode file"> 
        Choose whether to split and trim reads by barcode. The barcodes must be specified in a BARCODE file<br />
    	Barcodes should have the following format:<br />
    	ID BARCODE(line End)<br />
    	'#' marks a commentline
    	</option>
    </tab>
    <tab name="Parameters">   
        <option name="Remove Adapters"> This option enables you to remove adapters from reads (start and end only). Specify adapters in a
    	comma-separated list (e.g "CAGGTACG,CATTTTAG,AAATTGGAC").
    	</option>
    	<option name="Trim 3'/5' Poly-A/T prefixes"> This option can be covered by the filter settings.<br />
    	Specify whether PolyA/T prefixes/tails at the 5' end or PolyA/T at the 3' end of the reads should be trimmed.
    	</option>
        <option name="Discard reads with average quality below threshold"> 
        This option enables you to define a minimum average threshold in order to remove reads with low quality.
        Reads with an average read quality (mean over all single read-bases) below the defined threshold are discarded
        </option>
   		<option name="Trim reads from right until quality threshold is reached"> 
   		This option enables to trim reads by quality by defining a quality threshold. The reads can either be trimmed from only the right or from both sided ('Also trim from left') until a quality value above the set threshold is encountered.
   		Also trim from left"> Reads are trimmed from both sides applying the threshold set in "Trim reads by quality"
 		</option>
 		<option name="Reads containing Ns">
 		Determine whether to remove reads containing unknown bases (Ns).
   		</option>
   		<option name="Keep single ends if partner is discarded"> 
   		In case of paired-end data sets you can define whether to keep single ends even though the partner is discarded.
   		</option>
		<option name="Discard reads shorter than a given length"> 
		This option enables you to discard reads of a length shorter than a define minimum read length.
		This trimming process is performed after all other trimming operations.
		</option>
		<option name="Options for Illumina-data"> 
		In case of Illumina data: Specify the quality encoding, if known. If its set to 'auto', the node will make an educated guess.<br />
		Define whether the quality encoding should be converted to phred-based qualities.
		</option>
		<option name="Thread number"> Set the number of threads be used
		</option>
		<option name="Optional output folder for RRM"> Choose whether the output files should be stored in a separate output folder.
		In this case set the path to the folder.
		</option>
	</tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1<br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path to ReadFile2 <br></br>Cell 2 (Optional): Path to FilterFile<br></br>Cell 2 (Optional): Path to FilterFile</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1<br></br>Cell 1: Path to ReadFile2 (if given)</outPort>
    </ports>    

</knimeNode>
