<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_red.png" type="Source">
    <name>FastQC_v2</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        FastQC - A quality control tool for high throughput sequence data.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
    
        <intro>
         FastQC aims to provide a simple way to do some quality control checks on raw sequence data coming from high throughput sequencing pipelines. It provides a modular set of analyses which you can use to give a quick impression of whether your data has any problems of which you should be aware before doing any further analysis.
		<br></br>
		The main functions of FastQC are:
		<br></br>
		<br></br>
    	&#8226;Import of data from BAM, SAM or FastQ files (any variant)
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Providing a quick overview to tell you in which areas there may be problems
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Summary graphs and tables to quickly assess your data
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Export of results to an HTML based permanent report
    	
    	<br></br>
    	&#8226;Offline operation to allow automated generation of reports without running the interactive application
    	
    	<br></br>
		<br></br>
        Source: <a href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</a> 
        
        
        </intro>
        
        <option name="Folder for output files">Create all output files in the specified output directory.
                    Please note that this directory must exist as the program
                    will not create it.  If this option is not set then the 
                    output file for each sequence file is created in the same
                    directory as the sequence file which was processed.
		</option>	
		
        <option name="Number of threads">Specifies the number of files which can be processed
                    simultaneously.  Each thread will be allocated 250MB of
                    memory so you shouldn't run more threads than your
                    available memory will cope with, and not more than
                    6 threads on a 32 bit machine
        </option>
        
        <option name="Additional FastQC options.">For all additional FastQC options not offered above. 
        			Please consult the official FastQC documentation for assistance in configuring these options."
        </option>
        
        <tab name="Preference page">
        	<option name="HTE">
        		Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        		Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port name">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1 <br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path to ReadFile2.</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1<br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path to ReadFile2.</outPort>
    </ports>  
       
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
