<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>DepthOfCoverage</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Assess sequence coverage by a wide array of metrics, partitioned by sample, read group, or library.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This GATK tool processes an input bam file to determine coverage at different levels of partitioning and aggregation.
        	Coverage can be analyzed per locus, per interval, per gene, or in total.
        	The user gets several output tables contain different coverage summaries.<br></br>
        	 For further information, see <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/guide/tooldocs/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_coverage_DepthOfCoverage.php">GATK documentation of DepthOfCoverage</a>.
        </intro>
     
        
        <tab name="Options">
        	<option name="Outfile suffix">
        		Define the suffix that will be appended to the outfiles. (Default: Doc)
        	</option>
        	<option name="GATK Filter Terms">
        		Set additional GATK Read Filters that should be used for processing.
        		All Filters can be found in the <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/guide/tooldocs/">GATK online documentation</a>.
        	</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name= "GATK">
        <option name="GATK Memory">
        	Set the maximum Java heap size (in GB).
        </option>
        <option name="Path to BED file">
        	You can check this option to perform the analysis in certain genomic regions. 
        	You have to specify the intervals in a text file in BED format
        	(Format explained at <a href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/FAQ/FAQformat.html"> http://genome.ucsc.edu/FAQ/FAQformat.html</a>)
        	and select the file in the file browser.
        </option>
        <option name="Further options">
        	Set additional command line flags for the DepthOfCoverage.
        </option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Preference page">
        <option name="HTE">
        	Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        	Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        </option>
        <option name="Path to reference sequence">
        	Set the path to the reference reference sequence.
        	This will be done automatically if the path is already defined in the preference page.
        </option>	
        <option name="Path to GATK jar file">
        	Set the path to GenomeAnalysisTK.jar.
        	This will be done automatically if the path is already defined in the preference page.  
       	</option>
       	</tab>
	
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input BAM">
        	Input BAM file
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Output file">
        	Cell 0: File containing per locus coverage
        </outPort>
    </ports>
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
    </views>     
</knimeNode>
