<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_yellow.png" type="Source">
    <name>Segemehl</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Segemehl - Heuristic mapping of short read sequences with gaps
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
    
        <intro>
			Segemehl is a software to map short sequencer reads to reference genomes. Unlike other methods, Segemehl is able to detect not only mismatches but also insertions
			and deletions. Furthermore, Segemehl is not limited to a specific read length and is able to map primer- or polyadenylation contaminated reads correctly.
			Segemehl implements a matching strategy based on enhanced suffix arrays (ESA). Segemehl now supports the SAM format, reads gzip’ed queries to save both disk and 
			memory space and allows bisulfite sequencing mapping and split read mapping.<br></br>
			Source: <a href="http://www.bioinf.uni-leipzig.de/Software/segemehl/">http://www.bioinf.uni-leipzig.de/Software/segemehl/</a>
		</intro>
		<tab name="Alignment Parameters">
        <option name="Number of threads/ cores to use">Parallel threads &lt;n&gt; will make matching much faster on machines with  &lt;n&gt; multiple cores. Use them!</option>
        
        <option name="Use (multiple) split read mapping (e.g. for cDNA reads)">Segemehl supports (multiple) split read mapping. To activate the split read mapping,
				it is only required to give this option.</option>
        <option name="Use bisulfite mapping">Segemehl supports mapping of bisulfite-treated sequencing data where DNA fragments are treated with sodium bisulfite which 
        		results in the conversion of unmethylated cytosines into uracils while methylated cytosines remain unchanged. With bisulfite sequencing, it is possible 
        		to capture DNA methylation genomewide in an unbiased fashion with single-base resolution and is hence considered ‘gold standard’. Segemehl supports both 
        		currently used protocols for the construction of the bisulfite-treated libraries, namely methylC-seq  and BS-seq.</option>
      	
      	<option name="Alignment accuracy">This option controls the minimum alignment accuracy (in percent). All reads with a best alignment below this threshold will be discarded. </option>
      	<option name="Optional Parameters">
        		For each computing step, additional parameters can be specified. For a list of all parameters, see <a href="http://www.bioinf.uni-leipzig.de/Software/segemehl/">online Segemehl user manual</a>.<br />
        </option>    
      	
      	</tab>
      	<tab name="Adapter and polyA clipping">
        <option name="Clip 5' adapters">Using this option, Segemehl clipps adapter sequences of the 5'-ends of the reads before aligning them. Therefore you have to define 
        a adapter sequence.</option>
        <option name="Clip 3' adapters">Using this option, Segemehl clipps adapter sequences of the 3'-ends of the reads before aligning them. Therefore you have to define 
        a adapter sequence or in the case that you do not know the adapter sequence Segemehl can detect this sequence automatically.</option>
        <option name="Automatically clip polyA tails">Additionally, for cDNA-reads it is possible to automatically clip polyAtails . All clipping options may be combined.</option>
        <option name="Clipping accuracy [%]">You can control the clipping accuracy, selecting an integer value between 0 and 100 [%]. The default is set to 70%.</option>
        <option name="Type of clipping">All adapters and polyA-Signals will be soft-clipped. If you want hard-clipping, use this option.</option>
    	</tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">Cell 0: Path2ReadFile1<br></br>Cell 1 (Optional): Path2ReadFile2 (if paired end mapping is used)</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path2SAMFile<br></br></outPort>
    </ports>
    
        <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
		</views>
    
</knimeNode>
