<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>FeatureCounts</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        FeatureCounts is a highly efficient general-purpose read summarizing program that counts mapped reads to genomic features such as genes, exons, promoter, gene bodies, genomic bins and chromosomal locations.
        It can be used to count both RNA-seq and genomic DNA-seq reads.<br />
        FeatureCounts takes as input SAM/BAM files and an annotation file including chromosomal coordinates of features.
        featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features.<br />
        Source: <a href="http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/featureCounts/">http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/featureCounts/</a> <br /><br />
        For more details, see:
       	Liao et al, Bioinformatics 2013; doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656<br />
       <a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2013/11/30/bioinformatics.btt656.full.pdf">featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</a></intro>
        
        <tab name="Options">
        	<option name="Input">
        		Set the path to the GTF or SAF annotation file.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Output">
        		Set the path to the folder where the output file should be stored.
        	</option>
        	<option name= "Further options">
        	<b>File type</b>: Choose whether to use a GTF or a SAF annotation file.<br />
        	<b>Feature type used for counting</b>: Choose which feature type should be used for counting in the case a GTF file is used.<br />
        		(Default: 'exon') <br />
        	<b>Count multimapped reads</b>: Choose whether also not uniquely mapped reads should be counted. <br />
        	<b>Thread number</b>: Set the number of threads to be used. [1-16] <br />
        	<b>Perform read summarization at the feature level</b>: If specified, read summarization will be performed at the feature level (eg. exon level).
        		Otherwise, it is performed at meta-feature level (eg. gene level) <br />
        	<b>Feature type used for grouping results</b>: Specify the attribute type used to group features (eg. exons) into meta-features (eg. genes), when GTF annotation is provided.<br />
        		(Default: 'gene_id'; This attribute type is usually the gene identifier.)<br />
        		This argument is useful for the meta-feature level summarization.<br />
        	</option>
        	</tab>
        	<tab name="Preference page">
        	<option name="HTE"> Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        	Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        	</option>
			<option name="Path to featureCounts">
        		Set the path to the compiled featureCounts binary.
        		Theoretically all versions starting from <i>1.4.3</i> should be supported.
        	</option>
        </tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">
        	Cell 0: One or more SAM or BAM files
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">
        	Cell 0: Path to output file<br />
        	Cell 1: Command which was used to call the binary
        </outPort>
    </ports> 
    
        <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
</views>
    
</knimeNode>
