<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_yellow.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>Star</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        STAR aligns RNA-seq reads to a reference genome using uncompressed suffix arrays and is "splice aware".
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	STAR, a "splice aware" RNA-seq aligner, aligns RNA-seq reads to a reference genome using uncompressed suffix arrays.
        	Details are described in the publication: <a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/29/1/15">STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</a>
        	<br />Dobin et al, Bioinformatics 2012; doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635
        </intro>
        
        <tab name="STAR Options">
        	<option name="runMode">
        		<i>alignReads</i> or <i>generateGenome</i>:<br />
        		<br/>
        		<i>alignReads</i>: Aligns reads to a reference genome.<br />
        		<i>generateGenome</i>: Generates a genome index using one or more fastA files.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Use 2pass mapping?">
        		For the most sensitive novel junction discovery, it is recommended to run STAR in the 2-pass mode.
        		It does not increase the number of detected novel junctions, but allows to detect more spliced reads mapping to novel junctions.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Number of threads">
        		Number of threads to run STAR <i>genomeGenerate</i> or <i>alignReads</i>.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Optional parameters">
        		Parameters can be set like you would normally use them on the command line for this binary.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to genome indexes">
        		Path to the genome directory where genome indeces were generated using the STAR <i>generateGenome</i> mode.
        		This option is only needed when applying the <i>alignReads</i> mode.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to GTF file">
        		Path to the file with annotated transcripts in the standard GTF format.
        		STAR will extract splice junctions from this file and use them to greatly improve accuracy of the mapping.
        		While this is optional, and STAR can be run without annotations, using annotations is <b>highly recommended</b> whenever they are available.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Overhang">
        		The overhang specifies the length of the genomic sequence around the annotated junction to be used in constructing the splice junctions database.
        		Ideally, this length should be equal to the ReadLength-1, where ReadLength is the length of the reads.
        		For instance, for Illumina 2x100b paired-end reads, the ideal value is 100-1=99.
        		In case of reads of varying length, the ideal value is max(ReadLength)-1.
        		<b>In most cases, the default value of 100 will work as well as the ideal value.</b>
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to output folder">
        		Path where all the output data is stored.
        		The folder of the input files is used if no path is specified or the given path is invalid.
        	</option>
        </tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">
        	Input depends on the runMode:
        	<br />
        	<i>alignReads</i>: FastQ file(s) loaded with FileLoader (single- and paired-reads are supported).<br />
        	<i>generateGenome:</i> FastA file(s) loaded with FileLoader.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">
        	Cell 0: In case of <i>alignReads</i> path to SAM file, otherwise path to the folder containing the generated genome.<br />
        </outPort>
    </ports>    
    
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
	</views>
    
</knimeNode>
