<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./default.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>Art</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>ART (art_Illumina Q version) is a simulation program to generate sequence read data of Illumina
        sequencers. ART generates reads according to the empirical read quality profile summarized from
        large real read data. ART has been using for testing or benchmarking a variety of methods or tools
        for next-generation sequencing data analysis, including read alignment, de novo assembly, detection
        of SNP, CNV, or other structure variation.
        
        The current KNIME integration of art_Illumina can generate paired-end and  mate-pair reads sequencing simulation
        of Illumina sequencing platform. The first-read insertion rate is set to default 0.00009, the second-read insertion rate 
        to 0.00015 as well as the first-read deletion rate to 0.00011 and the second-read deletion rate to 0.00023.
        The outputs are two FASTQ read files (forward and reverse) out of diploid
        chromosomes of an individual (2 Fasta files). this integration is optimized for a trio 
        (father, mother, child) which is created by Frost only. Hence it is strictly suggested to use this integration 
        combined with Frost.
        
        We suggest to use the Art node combined with Frost as previous node which would facilitate a parallelized run. 
        The user can also start this node separately once Frost was already run. </intro>
        
        <option name="Path to the directory including the fasta and record files created by Frost">If started separately the user should use this option. If started 
            with Frost it will be ignored.</option>
        <option name="Read length (bp)">The length of reads to be simulated.</option>
        <option name="Mean size of DNA fragments">The mean size of DNA/RNA fragments for paired-end simulations.</option>
        <option name="Fold of read coverage">The fold of read coverage to be simulated or number of reads/read pairs generated for each amplicon.</option>
        <option name="Standard deviation">the standard deviation of DNA/RNA fragment size for paired-end simulations.</option>
        <option name="Turn off the masking of 'N' region">Default: Mask all regions with 'N' with a cutoff frequency of 1 
        in a window size of the read length for masking genomic regions. Click to turn off masking.</option>
        <option name="Turn on mate-pair condition">Click to turn on mate-pair condition. NOTE: art will automatically switch to a mate-pair simulation 
        if the given mean fragment size >= 2000.</option>
        <option name="Sequencing error free">Click to generate the zero sequencing errors.</option>
        <option name="Use separate quality profiles">Click to use separate quality profiles for different bases (ATGC).</option>
        <option name="Quiet">Click to turn off end of run summary.</option>
 
   
        <!-- possibly more options that can also be grouped by tabs -->
        <!--
        <tab name="Standard Options">
            
            <option name="short name of second option (like in the dialog)">description of second option</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Advanced Options">
            <option name="short name of first advanced option (like in the dialog)">description of first advanced option</option>
        </tab>
        -->
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Art input from Frost">Frost outputs<br></br>
        					If optional port is available this tool will automatically continue<br></br>
        					Otherwise the user has to specify the path of the directory with both haploid chromosomes
        					of each individual (father, mother and child) in fasta format.</inPort>
        <!-- possibly more input ports here-->
        <outPort index="0" name="Art outputs">Trio fastqs<br></br>
        					Cell 0: Fastq output for the forward read<br></br>
        					Cell 1: Fastq output for the reverse read<br></br>
        					Row 0: Read from father (chunkwise)<br></br>
        					Row 1: Read from mother (chunkwise)<br></br>
        					Row 2: Read from child (chunkwise)<br></br>					
        					</outPort>
        <!-- possibly more output ports here-->
    </ports>    
    <views>
        <!--view index="0" name="name of first view">Description of first view...</view-->
        <!--view index="1" name="name of second view">Description of second view...</view-->
    </views>
</knimeNode>
