<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_yellow.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>Star</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        STAR aligns RNA-seq reads to a reference genome using uncompressed suffix arrays and is "splice aware".
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	STAR, a "splice aware" RNA-seq aligner, aligns RNA-seq reads to a reference genome using uncompressed suffix arrays.
        	Details are described in the publication: <a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/29/1/15">STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</a>
        	<br />Dobin et al, Bioinformatics 2012; doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635
        </intro>
        
        <tab name="STAR Options">
        	<option name="runMode">
        		<i>alignReads</i> or <i>generateGenome</i>:<br />
        		<br/>
        		<i>alignReads</i>: Aligns reads to a reference genome.<br />
        		<i>generateGenome</i>: Generates a genome index using one or more fastA files.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Optional parameters">
        		Parameters can be set like you would normally use them on the command line for this binary.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to genome indexes">
        		Path to the genome directory where genome indeces were generated using the STAR <i>generateGenome</i> mode.
        		This option is only needed when applying the <i>alignReads</i> mode.
        	</option>
        	<option name="Path to output folder">
        		Path where all the output data is stored.
        		The folder of the input files is used if no path is specified or the given path is invalid.
        	</option>
        </tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">
        	Input depends on the runMode:
        	<br />
        	<i>alignReads</i>: FastQ file(s) loaded with FileLoader (single- and paired-reads are supported).<br />
        	<i>generateGenome:</i> FastA file(s) loaded with FileLoader.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">
        	Cell 0: In case of <i>alignReads</i> path to SAM file, otherwise path to the folder containing the generated genome.<br />
        </outPort>
    </ports>    
    
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
	</views>
    
</knimeNode>
