<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.8 http://knime.org/node/v2.8.xsd">
    <name>FilterSummary</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Node for filtering and summarizing the results of the Loss-of-Function workflow
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This node was especially developed for filtering and summarizing four VCF files produced by Pindel and GATK and annotated by VAT. 
        	It is the final node of the Loss-of-Function pipeline. 
        	It implements a coverage-based filter to reduce the number of false positive loss-of-function variants. 
        	Additionally it outputs three tables (with all variants, all loss-of-function variants and the filtered loss-of-function variants). 
        	It is possible to add annotations from NCBI gene_info (<a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov </a>), 
        	WikiPathways (<a href="http://wikipathways.org/index.php/WikiPathways"> http://wikipathways.org/index.php/WikiPathways </a>) 
        	and Reactome (<a href="http://www.reactome.org"> http://www.reactome.org </a>) 
        	about the affected genes to these tables. 
        	For generation of plots the node produces a file with various counts concerning the loss-of-function mutations found in the files.
			<br />
			Predecessor Loss-of-Function nodes: VAT, VCFLoader
    	</intro>
        
        
        <option name="Minimum coverage">
        	Set this filtering threshold according to the overall coverage. 
        	All variant sites that are covered by less reads are filtered out.
    	</option>
        <option name="Minimum fraction of supporting reads">
        	The fraction of reads that support the variant is another filter criteria. 
        	It excludes variants with less than a certain percentage (default 20 %) of the reads containing the variant.
    	</option>
        <option name="Write summary file">
        	If you tick this option, FilterSummary generates a file with counts of loss-of-function mutations. 
        	This file is useful to create plots.
    	</option>
        <option name="Add original VCF info and sample column">
        	Checking this options adds additional columns to the summary tables. 
        	The columns contain the original info and sample attributes of the VCF files.
    	</option>
        <option name="Annotate OMIM IDs from gene_info file">
        	This option adds a column with OMIM IDs to the output tables. 
        	Using this option you have to set the path to a NCBI gene_info file (it can be obtained at 
        	<a href="http://mirrors.vbi.vt.edu/mirrors/ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/gene/DATA/GENE_INFO/Mammalia/Homo_sapiens.gene_info.gz"> http://mirrors.vbi.vt.edu/mirrors/ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/gene/DATA/GENE_INFO/Mammalia/Homo_sapiens.gene_info.gz </a>).
    	</option>
        <option name="Annotate pathways from WikiPathways">
        	This option adds a column with pathways to the output tables. 
        	Using this option you have to set the path to a WikiPathways file (it can be obtained at 
        	<a href="http://wikipathways.org/wpi/cache/wikipathways_data_Homo%20sapiens.tab"> http://wikipathways.org/wpi/cache/wikipathways_data_Homo%20sapiens.tab </a>).
    	</option>
        <option name="Annotate number of interactions from reactome">
        	This option adds a column with the number of interactions to the output tables. 
        	Using this option you have to set the path to a Reactome file (it can be obtained at 
        	<a href="http://www.reactome.org/download/current/homo_sapiens.mitab.interactions.txt.gz"> http://www.reactome.org/download/current/homo_sapiens.mitab.interactions.txt.gz </a>).
    	</option>
        
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port 1">
			Cell 0: Path2VCFsnpFile (VCF file with SNPs from GATK)
    		<br />
    		Cell 1: Path2VCFindelFile (VCF file with indels from GATK)
		</inPort>
        <inPort index="1" name="In-Port 2">
        	Cell 0: Path2VCFinsertionsFile (VCF file with insertions from Pindel)
			<br />
    		Cell 1: Path2VCFdeletionsFile (VCF file with deletions from Pindel)
    		<br />
			The cell positions and inport numbers do not matter. Additional columns are ignored.
    	</inPort>
        <!--<outPort index="0" name=""></outPort>-->
    </ports>   
     
    <views>
        <view index="0" name=""></view>
    </views>
</knimeNode>
