<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>CombineGVCFs</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Combines any number of gVCF files that were produced by the Haplotype Caller into a single joint gVCF file.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	CombineGVCFs is meant to be used for hierarchical merging of gVCFs that will eventually be input into GenotypeGVCFs.
        	One would use this tool when needing to genotype a too large number of individual gVCFs;
        	instead of passing them all in to GenotypeGVCFs, one would first use CombineGVCFs on smaller batches of samples and then pass these combined gVCFs to GenotypeGVCFs.
        	Note that this tool cannot work with just any gVCF files - they must have been produced with the Haplotype Caller as part of the "single sample discovery" pipeline using the '-ERC GVCF' mode,
        	which uses a sophisticated reference model to produce accurate genotype likelihoods for every position in the target.<br />
        	For further information, see <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/gatkdocs/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_variantutils_CombineGVCFs.php">GATK documentation of CombineGVCFs</a>.
        </intro>
    
    	<tab name="Options">
        <option name="Path to output file">
        	Set the path to the directory where the combined gvcf files should be stored.
        </option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="GATK">
        <option name="GATK Memory">
        The GATK memory usage can be defined.
        </option>
        <option name="Path to BED file">
        	Coverage analysis can be restricted to genomic regions defined in a BED file.
        </option>
        <option name="Further options">
        	Commit further options to GATK.
        </option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Preference page">
        <option name="HTE">
        	Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        	Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        </option>
        <option name="Path to reference sequence">
        	Set the path to the reference reference sequence.
        </option>	
        <option name="Path to GATK jar file">
        	Set the path to GenomeAnalysisTK.jar.
        	This will be done automatically if the path is already defined in the preference page.  
       	</option>
       	</tab>

    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="GVCF In-Port">GVCF files in the first column</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Merged gVCF in the first column</outPort>
    </ports>
</knimeNode>
