<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>KGGSeq</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>KGGSeq is a software platform constituted of Bioinformatics and statistical genetics functions making use of valuable biologic resources and knowledge for sequencing-based genetic mapping of variants/genes responsible for human diseases/traits. Simply, KGGSeq is like a fishing rod facilitating geneticists to fish the genetic determinants of human diseases/traits in the big sea of DNA sequences. Compared with other genetic tools like plink/seq, KGGSeq paid more attention downstream analysis of genetic mapping. Currently, a comprehensive and efficient framework was newly implemented on KGGSeq to filter and prioritize genetic variants from whole exome sequencing data.</intro>
        
        <tab name="File Input Options">
            <option name="KGGSeq Jar">Path to the KGGSeq Jar File</option>
            <option name="VCF Input">Input VCF File</option>
            <option name="PED Input File">PED file holding the pedigree information</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="General Options">
            <option name="Build Version">Specifies the database and reference genome version</option>
            <option name="Composite Subject ID">KGGSeq uses a composite subject ID in the CVF file as "PedigreeName$IndividualID"</option> 
            <option name="Output Prefix">Prefix for all output files of this run"</option> 
            <option name="Output Format">File format, excel or csv"</option> 
        </tab>
        <tab name="Quality Cutoffs">
            <option name="Seq Qual"> Set the minimum overall sequencing quality score (Phred Quality Score) for the variant at</option>
            <option name="Seq MQ"> Set the minimum overall mapping quality score (Phred Quality Score) for the variant at</option>
            <option name="Seq SB"> Set the maximal overall strand bias score for the variant at</option>
            <option name="Gty Qual">Exclude genotypes with the minimal genotyping quality (Phred Quality Score) per genotype </option>
            <option name="Gty DP">Exclude genotypes with the minimal read depth per genotype &lt;  </option>
            <option name="Gty Sec Pl">Exclude genotypes with the second smallest normalized, Phred-scaled likelihoods for genotypes </option>
            <option name="Gty Af Ref">Exclude genotypes with the fraction of the reads carrying alternative allele &gt; = x% at a reference-allele homozygous genotype</option>
            <option name="Gty Af Het">Exclude genotypes with the fraction of the reads carrying alternative allele &lt; = x% at a heterozygous genotype.</option>
            <option name="Gty Af Alt">Exclude variants with the fraction of the reads carrying alternative allele &lt; = x% at a alternative-allele homozygous genotype</option>
        </tab>
        <tab name="Annotation Options">
        	<option name="...">For detailed explanations see: http://statgenpro.psychiatry.hku.hk/limx/kggseq/doc/UserManual.html</option>
            
        </tab>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port name"></inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port name">Currently returns inData</outPort>
    </ports>    
    <views>
        <view index="0" name=""></view>
    </views>
</knimeNode>
