<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source">
    <name>SamTools</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Provides access to many functionalities of SAMtools.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>The SamTools node enables the access to  several SAMtools utilities.<br />
        For more information, see <a href="http://samtools.sourceforge.net/samtools.shtml"> the
		       SAMtools help page</a></intro>
        
        
        <option name="Select utility">Choose which of the SAMtools utilities you want to use:
        <ul><li>cat: Concatenate BAMs. The sequence dictionary of each input BAM must be identical, although this command does not check this. </li>
        <li>faidx: Index reference sequence in the FASTA format</li>
        <li>calmd: Generate the MD tag</li>
        <li>fixmate: Fill in mate coordinates, ISIZE and mate related flags from a name-sorted alignment. </li>
        <li>flagstat: Print simple statistics of BAM file</li>
        <li>idxstats: Retrieve and print stats in the index file. The output is TAB delimited with each line consisting of reference sequence name, sequence length, # mapped reads and # unmapped reads.</li>
        <li>merge: Merge two sorted alignments. The header reference lists of the input BAM files (and the @SQ headers of  header sam file, if any), must all refer to the same set of reference sequences.</li>
        <li>phase: Call and phase heterozygous SNPs.</li>
         <li>reheader: Efficiently replace the header of a BAM file with the header of a SAM file</li>
         <li>rmdup: Remove potential PCR duplicates: if multiple read pairs have identical external coordinates, only retain the pair with highest
			mapping quality. In the paired-end mode, this command ONLY works with FR orientation and requires ISIZE is correctly set. It does not work for unpaired reads</li>
        	 </ul>
         </option>
        <tab name="Preference page">
        <option name="HTE"> Set a threshold for repeated execution.Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page. </option>
        <option name="Path to samtools"> Set the path to the SAMtools executable (only if no inport is available)</option>
        <option name="Path to reference sequence">Set the path to the reference sequence (only if no inport is available)</option>
 		</tab>
                      
        
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port name">Optional Inport<br></br>Cell 0: Path to input BAM/SAM file<br></br></inPort>
   		<outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to Outfile<br></br></outPort>
    </ports>

   <views>
   <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
   </views>

</knimeNode>
