<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./default.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>CaseControlAnalyzer</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Identification of significant genes in case control studies.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This node enables the identification of genes that are significantly more often affected by (LOF) variants in the case group than in the control group of a study.
        	Different methods can be applied to evaluate the significance of a gene.
        	The node requires a gene summary of the LOFSummary node as input.
        	A genetic background file (created by the GeneticBackgroundModel node) can be given to enhance the statistical power of the analysis.
        </intro>
        
        <option name="Summary file settings">
        	Set the field headers, if the gene summary is generated by another node than the LOFSummary.
        </option>
        <option name="Model (file) settings">
        	Set the model file headers, if it is generated by another node than the GeneticBackgroundModel.
        	Set a pseudo frequency for genes that have not been observed to carry any (LOF) variants.
        </option>
        <option name="Choose statistics and ordering">
        	Select the statistics to be computed and choose the p-values by which the resulting file is ordered.
        	The p-values are corrected for multiple comparison using the method of Benjamini-Hochberg (FDR).
        	The adjusted p-values are given in an extra column in the extended gene summary.
        </option>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Gene Summary">
        	Cell 0: Gene summary file containing a contingency table for each gene.
        </inPort>
        <inPort index="0" name="Background Model">
        	Cell 0: Genetic background model comprising the variant frequencies for each gene.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Extended Gene Summary">
        	Input gene summary extended by the computed and adjusted p-values ordered by the chosen statistic.
        </outPort>
    </ports>    
</knimeNode>
