<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>VEPSummary</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        This node generates summary files for annotated variants.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This node generates tab separated summary files of genetic variants annotated by the Variant Effect Predictor (VEP).
        	<ul>
        		<li>
        			The variant_summary contains a line for each variant in the VCF file.
        			Multi-allelic variants are split into two variants.
        		</li>
        		<li>
        			Each field in the matrix file contains the affection state of a transcript (rows) in an individual (columns).
        		</li>
        		<li>
        			The sample summary sums up the affected genes for each individual.
        		</li>
        	</ul>
        </intro>
        
        <option name="Path to CDS/GTF files">
        	A CDS or GTF file is required to compare the number of the affected transcripts to all transcripts of a gene.
        	The Ensembl CDS or GTF file which can both be downloaded here:
        	<br />
        	<a href="http://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html">http://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html</a>
        	<br />
        	To improve the performance of the node, it uses an internal representation of the given file which is stored at the location of the original file (ending with .gene_info).
        	Uncheck this box, if you do not want to use this .gene_info file.
        </option>
        <option name="Path to PED file">
        	Select a PED file which defines the case (phenotype = 2) and the control group (phenotype = 1).
        </option>
        <option name="Further options">
        	The node can be run in parallel mode which is recommended for file sizes up to 1 GB.
        	Larger files should be processed in sequential mode to prevent OutOfMemoryError exceptions.
        </option>
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="VCF file">
        	Cell 0: Path to the annotated VCF file.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Summary files">
        	Cell 0: Path to variant summary file.
        	<br />
        	Cell 1: Path to matrix summary file.
        	<br />
        	Cell 2: Path to sample summary file.
        	<br />
        </outPort>
    </ports>    
</knimeNode>
