<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source">
    <name>Mpileup</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
    Mpileup - Generates BCF or pileup files that can be used for SNP/Indel calling.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        Samtools-Mpileup belongs to the set of Samtools utilities and can generate BCF or pileup for a given BAM file.
        This requires that a BAM file is loaded using the BAMLoader node. Alignment records are grouped by sample 
        identifiers in @RG header lines. If sample identifiers are absent, the input file is regarded as one sample.<br></br>
        Source: <a href="http://samtools.sourceforge.net/">http://samtools.sourceforge.net/</a> 
         </intro>
         
        <option name="*************** Input Options ***************">
        </option>
         
        <option name="Use indexed reference genome">Use an indexed reference genome file for creating the BCF/pileup.
        The reference genome can be loaded using the BAMLoader node. If the genome is not already indexed, use the "Index reference genome first"
        option. Alternatively, genomes can be indexed using the <b>Faidx node</b>. 
        </option>
        
        <option name="Index reference genome first">By activating this option, an indexed reference file will be created.    
        </option>
       
        <option name="Quality is in the Illumina 1.3+ encoding">Assume the quality is in the Illumina 1.3+ encoding.  
        </option>
      
       <option name="Do not skip anomalous read pairs in variant calling">Activate if anomalous read pairs should be kept in analysis.
        </option>
       
       <option name="Disable probabilistic realignment for the computation of base alignment quality (BAQ)"> 
                	BAQ is the Phred-scaled probability of a read base being misaligned.
                	 Applying this option greatly helps to reduce false SNPs caused by misalignments. 
        </option>
        
        <option name="Coefficient for downgrading mapping quality for reads containing excessive mismatches">
        Given a read with a phred-scaled probability q of being generated from the mapped position, the new mapping 
        quality is about sqrt((INT-q)/INT)*INT. A zero value disables this functionality; if enabled, the recommended value for BWA is 50.
        </option>
        
        <option name="Extended BAQ computation">
        This option helps sensitivity especially for MNPs, but may hurt specificity a little bit. 
        </option>
        
        <option name="Cap mapping quality">
       	Max. mapping quality. 
        </option>
        
        <option name="Ignore RG tags">
       	 RG tags will be ignored.
        </option>
        
        <option name="Minimum mapping quality for an alignment to be used">Skip alignments with too small mapping quality
        </option>
        
        <option name="Minimum base quality for a base to be considered">Minimum baseQ/BAQ threshold for skipping bases
        </option>

        <option name="Activate if you want to exclude read groups listed in:">Reads listed in this file will be excluded
        </option>
        
        <option name="Activate if you want to restrict to a list of positions (chr pos) or regions (BED):">Similar to "Activate if you want to exclude read groups listed in". 
        BED or position list file containing a list of regions or sites where pileup or BCF should be generated.
        </option>
        
        <option name="Region in which pileup is generated">Enter a String which defines region where pileup is generated (chrom:start-stop).
        </option> 
        
        <option name="*************** Output Options ***************">
        </option>
        
        <option name="Generate BCF output (genotype likelihoods)">Compute genotype likelihoods and output them in the binary call format (BCF).
        </option>

        <option name="Generate uncompress BCF output">Output in uncompressed BCF
        </option>
        
        <option name="Output per-sample DP in BCF">Include per-sample read depth in output. <b>Requires BCF output format</b>.
        </option>

        <option name="Output per-sample strand bias P-value in BCF">Include per-sample strand bias P-value in output. <b>Requires BCF output format</b>.
        </option>        

        <option name="Output base positions on reads">Provides base positions in output file. <b>Disables BCF output</b>.
        </option>

        <option name="Output mapping quality">Provides mapping quality in output file. <b>Disables BCF output</b>.
        </option>    
        
        <option name="############### Options for Genotype Likelihood Computation ###############">(BCF only)
        </option>          
        
        <option name="Minimum fraction of gapped reads for candidates">Specifies the minimum fraction of gapped reads for candidates. 
        </option>   
  
        <option name="Coefficient for modeling homopolymer errors">Given an l-long homopolymer run, the sequencing error of an indel of size s is modeled as Input*s/l.
        </option>   
 
         <option name="Do not perform INDEL calling">
        </option> 
 
        <option name="Phred-scaled gap extension sequencing error probability">The gap extension sequencing error probability determines the length of called indel. Lower numbers lead to
        longer, increased numbers to shorter indels. 
        </option>              

        <option name="Phred-scaled gap open sequencing error probability">The gap open sequencing error probability determines the number of indel calls. The lower the gap open sequencing error probability, the more indels will be called.
        </option>
        
        <option name="Skip INDEL calling if the average per-sample depth is above"> Define threshold for skipping indel calling depending on average per-sample depth.
        </option> 
        
        <option name="Minimum gapped reads for indel candidates">
        </option> 
        
        <option name="Comma separated list of platforms for indels"> Comma dilimited list of platforms (determined by @RG-PL) from which indel candidates are obtained. It is recommended to collect indel candidates from sequencing technologies that have low indel error rate such as ILLUMINA
        </option> 
    </fullDescription>
    


    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port">Cell 0: Path to Samtools<br></br>Cell 1: Path to BAM file</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to Samtools<br></br>Cell 1: Path to BCF Output</outPort>
    </ports>   
    <views>
        <view index="0" name=""></view>
    </views>
</knimeNode>
