<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>GeneBasedAnalysis</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Analyzes case-control sequencing studies on gene level. 
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	This node analyzes case-control sequencing studies on gene level.
        	It enables the identification of genes that harbor significantly more LOF variants in the case than in the control group.
        	To this end, the node uses the matrix file generated by the LOFSummary node to compile contingency tables for each gene.
        	The contingency tables can directly be tested for significance by Fisher's exact test.
        	Moreover, it is possible to integrate LOF frequencies of a large population background to enhance the statistical power.
        </intro>
        
        
        <option name="Fisher's exact test">
        	Fisher's exact test can be performed based on different alternative hypothesis:
        	choose greater if you want to find more LOFs in cases than in controls, 
        	choose less if you want to find more LOFs in controls than in cases or 
        	two.sided if you look for any significant differences in cases and controls.
        </option>
        <option name="Hypergeometric background">
        	Two Fisher's exact tests are performed for cases vs. background and controls vs. background.
        	To get statistically sound results you have to set the Background population size parameter correctly.
        </option>
        <option name="Model file settings">
        	Select the column of the gene identifier and the gene-based background frequency in the model file.
        	Specify the correct background population size to get valid results.
        </option>
       
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Matrix file">
        	Matrix file generated by the LOFSummary node.
        </inPort>
        <inPort index="1" name="Background file">
        	Background file generated by the GeneticBackgroundModel node.
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Analysis summary">
        	Summary file of analysis.
        </outPort>
    </ports>    
    </knimeNode>
