<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./icon_d_green.png" type="Source">
    <name>SmartPhase</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Resolves haplotype phase of filtered rare variants in desired genomic regions to determine possible compound heterozygosity.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
		SmartPhase resolves haplotype phase in targeted genomic regions with the ultimate goal of informing on compound heterozygosity for clinical analysis.
		Through a combination of trio information and phase informative reads, high quality filtered variants of importance have their phase deduced and noted
		along with a confidence score. 
		<br></br>
    	<br></br>

		</intro>
        
        
        <option name="Gene Regions File">BED file specifying genomic regions of interest that are to be searched for filtered variants. 
        				No variants outside of these regions will be analysed. A valid BED file must be supplied. Optionally, if a column
        				with the header "name" is provided, the name of the genomic region will be displayed in the final output. Default 
        				column for this option is 4 (1-based).
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Filtered Variants File">File containing all potentially harmful variants to be analysed for compound heterozygosity to 
        				assist in clinical analysis. Accepts either VCF or output from a gemini db query. If not in VCF, must contain column
        				headers "chrom", "start", "ref", and "alt". NOTE: As gemini output is assumed in this case, "start" values must be 0-based! 
        				NOTE: Must be sorted by chrom and then start!
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="All Variants File">VCF file containing all variants of the patient. If trio information is available and should be used,
        				variants of all parents must also be contained within this file. Must be indexed.
                        </option>
                       
        <!--
        
         <option name="Reads">Comma separated list of BAM files to be used for phase informative reads during haplotype resolution. Must be sorted
        				by chromosome and then start. All BAM files must be indexed.
                        </option> 
        
        <option name="Minimum Mapping Quality">Comma separated list of mapping quality cutoff values to be used when examining reads. Each value
        				corresponds to the minMapQ for an input BAM file and thus there must be an equal number of arguments for both options.
                        </option> 
                        
     	-->
                        
        <option name="Patient ID">Official ID of patient to be analyzed. Must be equal to patient ID used in AllVariants.vcf.
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Folder for smartPhase output files">Output directory where all predictions and statistics should be written to.
                        </option>   
                        
        <option name="Trio Information Available">Boolean flag indicating if trio information is available and should be used while phasing.
                        </option>
                        
        <option name="Family Pedigree File">Pedigree file containing familial information indicating which IDs correspond to the father and mother
        				of the patient. Used when analyzing vcf file to know which columns to examine for variant infos. ID used for "Patient ID" must
        				also be used here.
                        </option>        
        
        <tab name="Preference page">
        	<option name="HTE">
        		Set a threshold for repeated execution.
        		Only used if HTE is enabled in the preference page.
        	</option>
        </tab>
   
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="In-Port name">Cell 0: Path to ReadFile1 <br></br>Cell 1: Path to ReadFile2.</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Out-Port">Cell 0: Path to compound heterozygote prediction output file.<br></br>Cell 1: Path to statistics output file.</outPort>
    </ports>   
    <views>
        <view index="0" name="STDOUT / STDERR">The node offers a direct view of its standard out and the standard error of the tool. </view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
